[Music]
hi everyone we are back for another
episode of the usada pitch and i'm
joined today by alison wagner who plays
an exceptionally important role here at
usana she is our director of athlete and
international relations which means that
she actually works closely with athletes
and organizations around the world to
help ensure the athlete rights are
upheld within the global anti-doping
system and the athletes have a seat at
the table allison is so well suited for
this role in part because she is
actually an olympian herself and earned
a silver medal at the atlanta 1996
olympic games alison thank you for your
time today and welcome to your first
episode of the pitch
thanks glad to be here great let's get
started can you tell us more about your
athletic career
sure yeah so i was a swimmer uh i found
the individual medley
i was a 96 olympic silver medalist and
former world record holder and so i swam
in the 90s and then again 2005 to 8.
awesome can you tell us about your
access to a level playing field or lack
thereof during your career
sure yeah my experiences during my
swimming career really motivated me to
work in the world of sport and
specifically now with usada and the
anti-doping system
i raced against multiple athletes that
were later proven to have doped
and progressively over time it was more
and more disheartening and discouraging
that my sacrifices and dedication to
competing fairly weren't wasn't that
dedication and the sacrifices weren't
being protected uh by those people in
power
and positions of influence within sport
so i was really frustrated and
you know it was a really hard process to
go through to
keep racing and winning silver medals to
athletes who were later proven to have
doped
so uh in watching the russia scandal
unfold
i decided that i would try to do
something within sport because i knew
athletes clean athletes around the world
and especially here in the usa were
going to be experiencing what i
experienced which was
an unfair playing field and
a lack of
sanctioning that protected clean
athletes and protect a clean playing
field
awesome so there's a lot of different
avenues for advocating for clean sport
why did you want to take on your current
role with usada in particular
well i've been a fan of usada for quite
a while
i believe that there needs to be more
outspoken leaders in service to athletes
and i feel like usada has been that for
athletes in a lot of ways over many
years
and i was thrilled to
apply and then get this role at usada
for that reason
awesome what do you hope to accomplish
in the next couple of years
well i hope to help move the needle and
make a positive impact and service to
athletes i think that every area of
sport and sport governance and the
anti-doping system
every system in place in sport and every
system that should be in place and sport
should be more athlete informed
athletes have a lot of expertise a lot
of wisdom and they are ultimately who we
are serving and they make up the olympic
and paralympic movement and they're the
ones we watch at the olympic and
paralympic games i believe we need to
serve these athletes with more
dedication and um with more of an eye on
improving the system to serve them
better
definitely well allison thank you so
much for sharing we'll leave it there
for now but i can't wait to have you
back on soon
thanks so much
thanks for listening everyone and we'll
be back for another episode of usada
pitch soon
[Music]
you